Test Okay, thanks. Good evening everyone. I now call to order this October 28th meeting of Lancaster City Council welcome a
few Reminders here at the top of our meeting during this During our meeting this evening there will be opportunities for public comment The first general public comment period is for residents that have registered in advance to speak about items that are not on the agenda residents may also comment on individual legislative items that's section 9 on our agenda this evening finally a second public comment period will be at the end
of the agenda for any other speakers wishing to address council about items not previously addressed all speakers will be reminded to begin with our name and block of residents for our meeting record and adjust our comments toward council please be advised that public comment is not a question answer period all comments are limited to three minutes per speaker and to keep time I i will be using this timer light it will turn green when a speaker begins it will flash yellow when there is one minute remaining and it will flash red when we've reached three minutes
if a speaker continues after three minutes they will be asked to end their comment i appreciate everyone's cooperation to maintain order and respectfulness and also equal time this evening also just a reminder this meeting is being recorded and this is an excellent opportunity
to silence your devices if you haven't done so already lastly an announcement before we get our begin our meeting tonight i would like to announce that council has not yet received the community benefit agreement being negotiated with carissa technology parks while this is disappointing i want to ensure the public that the delay is not because work is is not excuse
me it's not because work is not being done in fact it has been ongoing and i appreciate that will take time to deliver an agreement to council that is more than perfunctory
I have a meeting scheduled later this week to receive updates and I will I
have been told that we can expect that this will come before council in November I remain committed to keeping the public informed as I receive updates
and now for all of those who are willing and able please rise for the Pledge of Allegiance mr. Harris would you please call the roll of members yes madam president mr. men here mr. Roya here mr. Cleese yeah miss Craig here miss Diaz here mr. Hirsch yeah here we will first take up the approval of the minutes of our October 14th 2025 meeting of counsel motion to approve second we have a motion and a second councillors any comments on our minutes hearing none mr. Harris mr. Wynn aye mr. Arroyo aye mr. Cleese aye miss Craig all right miss Diaz mr. Hirsch all right president Baker aye the next item on our agenda is
proclamations honors awards and resolutions of recognition mr. Harris confirming that we have none of those on our agenda this evening we do not matter president thank you all right that will take us into our first public comment period again this is reserved for residents that did contact the city clerk prior to the meeting to request the opportunity to address counsel
again duration of comments is limited to three minutes mr. Harris we have speakers for this comment period we do madam president first is Susan Gomez thank you and for speakers our microphone is right there and if you're the first speaker you may need to turn it on if it's not on already for you Thank You mr. Harris perfect good evening good evening susie gomez 800 block at east orange street um just going to jump right into it um playing devil's advocate has disrupted an entire conservative city what's right should be right what's wrong is wrong what's good is good and what's bad is evil we the citizens and residents of lancaster pa city are affected by the unfinished roads rerouting of buses potholes car repairs closure of kunzler and many other prominent businesses lack of leadership zero accountability transparency is out the window leaving us to face these conditions every day young adults dying in numbers lack of distribution of funding projects dismantled permits censored and contracts given to outsiders who can't complete major roads out of respect to commuters and taxpayers not to mention the 100 students walking out of mccaskey to join a movement that they should have never been a part of because the government shutdown is based on undecided politicians who can't seem to agree on who the money is going to be spent on the amount of misuse of funds in the united states of america should never harm any child from being educated especially when pre-planned budgets take place before the opening of any school and funding has been applied prior to any student entering any school no one can operate projectively on empty budgets every child comes with a price and government funding is always applied not to mention school taxes taken out as well to balance a deficit if attended to for the needs of the and for the needs and purposes it was taken for in the first place it shouldn't be hard to do that did i mention the amount of young and old unhoused homelessness crimes and so much more now we have animals being displaced on top of the hazardous water where the people well sorry where the police department can no longer be responsible to house stray animals because the city has yet to repair the HVAC system as promised so these animals have to travel to Philadelphia etc employees jobs are jeopardized la academia students still waiting on repairs to be completed just an overwhelming amount of issues that Jamie Arroyo will be left with as a
landlord and business owner for over five years in the city or the next mayor
but I do thank the police department for stepping in to volunteer with these animals because the Humane League and other shelters if any well they have other plans so we are left with a mouthful of problems and taxation is still on the rise while developers get breaks and colleagues get to decide our future and unskilled workers get to run our city down to the ground thank you mr. Harris our next speaker for this period yes madam president next is James Rokowitz is mr. Rokowitz here this evening we'll go to our next commenter and I'll recall his name at the end next is Ian I'm sorry Ian McAndrew good
evening I'm Ian McAndrew I'm a Lancaster resident and I'm very concerned about
the proposed data centers I feel this may be a little premature given that you don't have the CBA in hand yet but frankly my understanding of the CBA is that it's very short on benefits for the community and very short on enforcement mechanisms for violating its own policies what happens two years down the road when something goes wrong I look forward to this council and anybody involved paying particular attention to the community benefits portion of the community benefits agreement I think I'm gonna wait for anything else thank you
for your time away for everything else until you have a CBA and we'll do this
next thank you our next comments are mr. Harris next is Sarah Berman good evening thank you all for your dedicated service to our fine town my name is Sarah Berman I'm reside on the 100 block of North Mary Street I'm also here to express my concerns about the data centers the environmental impact both on water and energy not to mention the extreme light and sound pollution that people who
are already living nearby these centers are experiencing it is absolutely life-changing
and not for the better and the thing that's happening now and i thank you very much for the quick update at the beginning about the cbas i'm very also much looking forward to seeing how that has hopefully been improved because as Ian mentioned as of now it lacks any enforcement any teeth a lot of nebulous yeah we'll see what we can do about that from the developer side that just makes me very nervous and the other thing that I think we need to be reminding ourselves of is all of these potential risks that we're taking is just for phase one there's going to be a phase two and we're not even planning for that yet and so no one is going to come in to any community and spend billions of dollars not to get to phase two we need to know what that entails the only thing they've really said about phase two is that in general it's all just more more energy more light more sound more space and we already discussed the CBA and I look forward to that and the last thing I want to say is that I hope that this experience is teaching us the urgency of potentially reforming some of our zoning laws so that we can catch up to tech as it is today because these these data centers were approved under nebulous circumstances because they were classified incorrectly as warehouses and we all know that they are not we just don't have the laws that meet the story and we have to come up with some more robust options to protect ourselves in our community thank you very much thank you mr. Harris our next speaker this evening yes madam president next to charlotte altemeyer good evening hi there thank you my name is charlotte altemeyer i'm a resident on the 200 block of charlotte street as it is charlotte on charlotte uh first i'm very concerned that something as consequential as a multi-billion dollar data center was able to move forward without public input i believe we should be investigating how that was able to happen second the draft community benefit agreement as it's currently written lacks details around benefits for the community it offers soft language around harm avoidance i recommend a working group be brought
together to strengthen that community benefit agreement it sounds like there is work in process
there but certainly calling out the inclusion of accountability and mechanisms to ensure that the agreement is honored and lastly i would call out that the events surrounding the data center in general have broken my trust and my confidence and i would ask that everyone sitting on this council think about how this council had can bring back trust in its citizens like me and others it's of major concern thank you thank you mr harris our next speaker next speaker is carlos gonzalez thank you i do have a note that mr gonzalez has requested interpretation services this evening
so he will have his three minutes for comment and then i will allow additional time for the
interpretation good evening first of all good evening i would like to give a copy of this reading he has copies of the translation in english that he would like to provide to each of you thank you good evening city council member member the consejo municipal gracias por la oportunidad de estar aqui esta noche mi nombre es carlos gonzalez he sido residente at 321 south n street during durante 37 años estoy aquí en nombre de mi bloque de mi cuadra 300 bloque del vecindario de saúl street donde hay más de 40 familia que vive en este lado de la de la acera de la calle también soy parte de saúl concern and neighbor y hemos estado aquí para mejorar la vida de los de los miembros del vecindario estoy aquí en este momento para comentar sobre una preocupación del vecindario que está teniendo lugar ahora en estos momentos el alleyway 59 que está detrás de la cuadra del 300 bloque del sawen street fue anteriormente un callejón privado que durante muchos años fue vigilado y atendido por nosotros por los vecinos de ese bloc ahora el area way 59 por varios años como 10 años ha sido pertenece pertenece a la ciudad y se suponía que ellos que la ciudad se iba a preocupar del mantenimiento y de la recogida de nieve y de todo lo que había pues durante todos estos años eso no se hizo y nosotros seguimos como vecindario dándole mantenimiento y cuidado a ese alleyway la ciudad aprobó unos permisos para una persona externa a nuestro vecindario que no vive en nuestra comunidad que no es parte de nuestro neighborhood. Y para que él usara un lote que está detrás del alleyway, que es parte del alleyway, un lote que él iba a construir un garaje grande con un parqueo para poder traer su negocio aquí, un negocio comercial en la que utiliza vehículos de heavy load, de carga grande, clase 3, cuatro y cinco más de diez mil libras de capacidad de libre peso los vecinos de saúl street de saúl marshall street se negaron a proveerle un acceso a través de saúl marshall street para que él pudiera entrar a su negocio pero fue negado porque el vecindario se impuso a eso. Entonces, en este momento, el dueño de este negocio adquiere ingresos a través de Dolphin Street and Juniata Street para poder tener acceso a su lugar. Y el alleyway ahora está invadido por vehículos de más de 10,000 libras de peso en la que está afectando a la comunidad al barrio y es un peligro para los niños del vecindario los niños que juegan normalmente detrás de la ley detrás de las casas y además que hay un pasillo constante de estudiantes de las
tres escuelas mccaskey washington school and middle school pasan constantemente
by that alleyway, with their parents and their families entering the school and arriving
at the school.
So our biggest concern is how to prove that someone can do this type of commercial activity in a neighborhood that is residential.
That is our biggest concern.
And we want an answer. You already have an answer.
And what could you do to protect us in this aspect? Thank you.
mr. Gonzalez we will allow additional time for inter English interpretation and I appreciate that you have provided this to us in writing as well okay so good evening City Council members thank you for the opportunity to be here tonight my name is Carlos Gonzalez I have been a resident of 321 South Ann Street for 37 years I am here on behalf of the 300 block of South Hand Street neighborhood and the more than 40 families living there. I am also part of South Anne Concerned Neighbors. I am here to comment on a neighborhood concern taking place now. Alley 59 which is behind the 300 block of South Anne Street
was previously a private alleyway that for many years was watched and serviced
by the neighbors. Now alley 59 belongs to the city however the neighbors continue to provide maintain and watch over the alley because the city doesn't do it the city approved permits for an external individual who is not part of the neighborhood to establish his commercial business headquarters in an empty lot nearby which only has access through alley 59 the commercial business is a trucking and hauling company using class 3 trucks and higher class 3 trucks and higher, weighing more than 10,000 pounds. South Marshall Street neighbors refused and denied access through the South Marshall Street nearby alley. Now the alley 59 only access can be through Juniata Street
or Dauphin Street.
These are the concerns of having a large vehicle commercial business headquarters in residential neighborhood. Danger to neighborhood children who play and walk
and go to school and back from school,
damage to alley roadways, continued truck weight, causing asphalt damages, large potholes and cracked roads that are trip hazards to the pedestrians, parking limitations and financial stress on families from limited parking availability. Years ago, neighbors were allowed to park behind the houses without blocking each other. Presently, neighbors are ticketed for parking behind their houses
due to this business demand.
Continued altercations of upset neighbors and the business owner. The upset neighbors continue to confront the business owner in a physical and upset manner. How could the city provide protections for a one single business and not favor the more than 40 families in the neighborhood affected by this business choice of establishment in a residential zone? Please review the construction permits and provide solutions to benefit and protect the residential neighborhood.
sincerely Carlos Gonzalez
Thank you very much Mr. Harris, we have additional speakers for this period
We do madam president. Thank you
Next is Bob Carlson. Good evening Just got a little closer to the microphone you can lift it up if he needs that. Thank you. Perfect. Okay Thank you all and I just wanted to reiterate what the other said about the data center And I moved here to this area about two years ago from Texas, where in Texas they had some problems with data centers, where they, I don't know if you've read about them.
But anyway, I moved here basically for the quality of life. Lancaster is a great area, and I investigated a lot of different areas up here in the northeast to get away from those Texas summers.
and Lancaster just looked like a perfect place and now I see that you are thinking about having data centers come into the community which I'm not you know anti-business I'm pro-business but there has to be a good reason for bringing them in here and if they're coming in where they're going to abuse our resources our electric grid and our water system and you know just take
advantage of us and they use this term data center and a factory I mean they a warehouse I'm sure those terms were all focus grouped so that you could like them where they're really they should be what they they're more like a technical factory would be more appropriate and so if you said I'm going to have a factory stuck in your neighborhood you might be a little more hesitant about letting them in but that's more of what they are because they're going to be polluting the area with noise and air pollution and they're going to be draining our
resources so just think about what letting into the community and how
they're going to pay for it and you know take care of the community they're not going to bring bring it in a lot of employment there's going to be very
little employment and a good case in point is today amazon just laid off 14 000 workers and because of ai so more likely what they're doing is you know they'll bring in a minor amount of employment to the area but not much so think about what you're doing thank you mr harris we have additional speakers for this period yes madam president next speaker is Bruce Dwayne Mungay thank you mr. Harris it moves but sometimes not as easily
okay thank you that's perfect thank you
1620 Robert Road since Jimmy Carter was president of the United States I've been
here a while i've seen a lot of changes but first i want to go through some definitions
make sure everybody's on the same page when i use these words one a warehouse is a place to store physical items it's not a empty building manufacturer is a place where raw materials are turned into the physical final physical form now i do notice that where this glenn road is excuse me nervous it's zoned suburban manufacturing it is not a warehouse or whatever so the zoning is wrong and what is an ai or data center and we always heard these terms Well, they're a physical facility that houses computing, network equipment like servers,
storage systems, and other IT interstructural needed to run applications and manage data.
When we think of AI, we kind of think of maybe a bunch of computers sitting there in a dark room with their little lights buzzing around and everything's hunky-dory. We've seen this all on sci-fi movies, Star Trek, and everything else. But let's talk about how big data centers can be. The smallest is 5,000 to 20,000 square feet and uses 500 to 2,000 servers. Typical power consumption is 1.5, 125 megawatt. Medium is larger than a small, of course. and it uses 150 kilowatts to that's that's wrong sorry misprint sorry hyperscale which is what
the ones that greenfield are can be over 100 100 000 square feet in 20 to 100 000 milliwatt
use. Now there are some cons, pros to data centers. Yes, they can help stimulate economy, maybe. But they increase tax revenue, that's good. And maybe they can be used to fund community services and infrastructure. And they help the technology advancement of the area in business it attracts other business because the cause of them in the
instruction is also leads to improvements in local structures such as
roads Mr. Monk I appreciate your comments we've reached three minutes if you have a final a final thought to add sorry I was just wondering when we're gonna have a public hearing on the data center first it didn't happen
I looked at the Planning Commission. They said October 5th, which is a Sunday. Thank you.
Mr. Harris, do we have additional speakers for this period? Yes, Madam President. Next is Tony D'Astra.
Thank you. Good evening. Tony D'Astra, 700 Block of New Holland Avenue. So I came here tonight to talk about the communications trouble that the city has been having.
because if any look i live and breathe government live streams all right uh i'm glad that the one last week functioned well because i was at langster township running a live stream and i can
participate in the budget hearing process he's still the budget is our most transparent part of city government as per the charter in my opinion so i'm glad that things worked well and i actually
to thank you council president because two weeks ago i believe it was i saw your sense of urgency
and i appreciate that because that is desperately needed for the functioning of these systems
as another resident mentioned there are trust issues right now especially and the live stream and its functionality is critical to maintaining a level of trust with the public because even if we disagree on what should or shouldn't be done in our community we deserve to understand how we got to those conclusions so i'll use the rest of my time tonight to say about the data center that i agree with the residents here tonight uh this is a massive concern and i also hope to see more of a sense of urgency from counselors moving forward here because i'm still of the opinion that
if we can persuade our zoning officer to rescind his decision letter in error it gives us as the the public a better footing to combat these data centers and have more leverage to get
agreements with teeth there's been a draft of a cba circulated amongst members of the public
which heavily disappointed in because it doesn't provide accountability for the individuals who
are coming to put this money in the community there's no guarantee that our well-being is going to be protected and so i'm i'm at a loss for words because these are the moments where we desperately need our government to demonstrate that they are in line with the community on these issues of concern we're looking at all you guys and all who come after you because this will be something that goes on for a while because we've we as a municipality as a city not you guys
exclusively not the mayor all of us are in this we are all stakeholders in the city of Lancaster
and any legal fight we want to have and unfortunately this has gotten to the territory where we are definitely going to have a legal fight of some kind and we want to know that the government is with the public not against the public. Thank you. Thank you. Mr. Harris confirming
we don't have any additional speakers for this period. We do not Madam President. We missed
James Rolkowitz in the beginning. I'll just call that name in case he has come in. I don't think so. Okay just confirming. Thank you everyone. We'll move to the next portion of our agenda this evening which is reports requested by council. Mr. Harris confirming that we have none of those this evening is that right we do not matter president you interim reports of committees of council confirming that we have none of those we also have none of those thank you very much then that will take us into our legislative agenda this evening we begin with our first item which is legislative legislative budget transfers council royal Thank You council president as you're aware the city is self insured for workers compensation costs every year funds to pay workers compensation claims are included in the individual department budgets but those claims are paid from administrative services budget so each quarter we shift money from the departments where those injured workers have made claims to the administrative services budget to cover the cost for
the third quarter of the year workers comp claims were made by city police
officers firefighters and public work staff a total of fifty eight thousand
three hundred twenty nine dollars and eighty eight cents is being moved from the police bureau fire bureau and public works budgets to administrative services
because this money is being moved between departments this requires city council approval so i make a motion to approve the third quarter workers compensation transfers totaling fifty
eight thousand three hundred twenty nine dollars and eighty eight cents as proposed second thank
you council roy we have a motion and a second counselors any comments on the transfer comments on the budget transfer from the public hearing none mr harris mr mann aye mr arroyo aye mr glees aye miss craig aye miss diaz aye mr hirsch aye and president baker aye we'll move to our next item b which is ordinances for final passage we first have administration bill number eight 2025 mr harris an ordinance of the lancaster city council authorizing the enforcement of section 3 1 1 2 a 3 of the pennsylvania motor vehicle code relating to traffic control signals by recording violations using an automated red light enforcement system approved by the pennsylvania department of transportation providing for the repeal of inconsistent ordinances providing for the severability of the ordinance and providing that the ordinance shall take effect in accordance to the Pennsylvania law motion to approve second we have a motion and a second councillor Diaz this is coming up through public safety we reviewed this at the committee in the last council meeting do you have anything additional just in case anyone has not understanding of the red light it's it's basically the ordinance is authorizing the city of Lancaster to implement and
enforce automated red light cameras to designate the the intersection in
accordance to Pennsylvania law vehicles will be recorded running red lights under the section 31 12 a and 3 of the Motor Vehicle Code will be also subject to a hundred dollars civilian penalty the violations will not be considered a criminal conviction or affect insurance points I just thought people should know
that this is something that they should know that they would get penalized but
at least you will not get points for it that's all i have thank you very much counselor diaz any additional comments from council on the on the bill thank you i will just say that we had a lot of support from the community at our previous meeting and our first reading for this one and i'm excited to be able to bring this forward on council i think anything we can do to
protect our residents from being injured whether they're in another vehicle they're walking they're biking because someone is being careless and running a red light is important and we'll go
a long way to meet our vision zero initiatives and goals i'm also pleased as deputy director cindy mccormick presented to us that this initiative doesn't bring in any additional income to the city it simply pays for itself and any income beyond that goes directly back to pen dot so we're just thankful to be able to have this program for the pure reason of saving lives and
and keeping people safe any additional comments from the public on the bill good evening i'll
just remind everyone to please begin with your name and block of residence for the meeting record good evening is 300 block of south and green light red light i want to communicate the rollout process, how that's so important. Notification communication can be so confusing in the pockets of Lancaster. I'm not sure how many residents even know what Visit Zero is. They're so focused on their own day-to-day lives. So I would love to be a liaison or hear more about what is the
rollout process going to be. I'm very sure that if it happens off the back, you get a final right away that's going to be cause friction as good and well intended as this is you want to ensure that their drivers and the road folks are in harmony and I want to know what the time frame is for when tickets will get informed will be implemented and again information thank you I think director Campbell I believe 90 days is the warning period so for the first 90 days of the program there'll be warnings issued not actual fines council president i believe it's 60. 60 days yeah thank you very much council hirsch and i i also wanted to add um just to speak to your question my understanding
is that the implementation is not going to start until the spring of 2026 because the cities upon getting this uh should we approve it um they would have to go out and and procure a vendor
for the cameras so there will be a little bit of a lag time but I think once that's implemented the city yeah will be very important to communicate
out to residents that that they're in effect and you know that 60 grace 60 day grace period it's communicated when it is and then when fines would commence absolutely thank you appreciate that context counselor sure thank you I'm
glad you mentioned that councilman Hirsch about the vendors because I was very concerned as you know we ride up down the turnpike and they do scamming with those automatic cameras that's a big scam item out getting people to get pictures of your car and your license and they send you a ticket and it's not
even you so I want to know what security is council looking to have that these cameras are up I would like to know where they're being places at every red light within the city and like Izzy had said I'm very concerned about what we're
going to do to let the public know because a lot of times we don't division zero we have no enforcement of the bike laws we do everything to keep bikers safe but i'm a driver and i see bikers all the time not obeying the laws and i want to know what vision zero what else are we going to do to keep residents safe not just the bikers not just the walkers but us as automobile drivers when are we going to enforce the things that they do that make it unsafe thank you thank
you may I venture to just quick respond to miss Byrd's comment yes I'll just responded with two things I would I would say you had asked where the locations are so I'll just read them real quickly because they're there in the ordinance the primary locations being considered are East King Street at
Lime, West King Street at Water, Columbia Ave at West End Ave, North Lime and East Walnut, and Manor, Hershey, Southwest and Ave. Alternate locations have been identified although my understanding is they won't be implemented right away so these alternative locations that have been listed are North Plum and East
Chestnut race and Marietta Ave North Lyme and East Orange Street and North Plum and East Walnut Street so those are the locations I'll just say one other thing just because you know I think you know I'm passionate about this issue right I would say when we make it safer for people that are walking for people that are biking we actually there's a byproduct of that which is that we end up making it safer for drivers um and you know it's going to take time it's going to take implementation of you know infrastructure and and you know the the the daylighting and and stuff for example that's like kind of the step one and you know it'll be an evolution over time i think so i hope that speaks to some of your concerns that you brought up thank you counselor hirsch
additional comments from the public on the bill tony dash the 700 block new holland avenue uh last time i was here i advocated for only one amendment to this which would be to allow these hundred dollar penalties to be paid with some level of either educational opportunity or community service for example uh driver training like you run a red light hey i understand there's a need to build that programming or rely on pen dot for some assistance but actually um i do think that it should be passed as is and instead what council should work on since there will be some lag time here is a more comprehensive ordinance change so
that not only these penalties but any applicable penalties any applicable fines in the city of
lancaster could be paid through some sort of volunteer service or educational opportunity i'm including even street sweeping in this like we have ms4 requirements i think it's module one public outreach and it could be important for our ms4 guidelines to integrate some sort of
educational opportunity as a essentially a penalty if you're not going to move your car for street sweeping uh so that's really all i came to say is that i think we need to especially in this economic time be focused on ways we can bring the public's understanding up to a level that we're all trying to get to without hurting their wallets but time is money so there still will be some sting when you have a penalty associated so that's what i came to say and i'm looking forward to these improvements thank you any additional comments from the public on the bill hearing none mr. Harris mr. man aye mr. Arroyo aye mr. Glees aye
miss Craig all right miss Diaz mr. Hirsch aye and president Baker aye next item on the agenda this evening is administration bill number 9 2025 mr.
Harris and ordinance the City Council of the City of Lancaster Lancaster County Pennsylvania approving a change in use of American Rescue Plan Act funds granted to the Lancaster Recreation Commission for renovation of Price Elementary School to convert it to a new community center into renovation of the existing Lancaster Recreation Center located at 525 Fairview Avenue authorizing the appropriate city officials to take any and all next actions necessary to accomplish the same providing for the repeal of inconsistent ordinances providing for the severability ordinance and providing The ordinance shall take effect as provided by Pennsylvania law motion to approve Second we have a motion and a second councillors. Thank you We reviewed this at our committee of the whole meeting at the beginning of the month and again at our last meeting for a first
Reading just as a reminder
Because of the original project that these funds were allocated to is is not happening
The Lancaster rec has requested use of the funds for their existing building
improvements can include much-needed HVAC improvements and potentially other improvements to the elevated walkway and other areas of the building for community investment any additional comments from council on the bill council president counselor I'm Ed Thank You council president and we all want to see this project succeed my only comment is that I hope that we do get a follow
up report from the rec Commission on the status of the repairs that are being made and a final maybe even a walkthrough of the HVAC system and the walkway when it is completed thank you very much counselor met I think we can
arrange that maybe before and after would be would be good additional comments from counsel on the bill comments from the public sir I would just ask if you're gonna make comment you'll need to come there just for our meeting record and for everyone and please begin with your name and block of
residents I was just gonna say that I hope that local businesses hired to
perform that HVAC work thank you very much just be special memory and tell us how much money that was and I will open the bill and take a look at that because I don't have my notes in the last meeting let's see I apologize have my other notes in front of me director Campbell or Delves do you have the amount that's remaining to be spent on the reallocated projects close by you're probably gonna find it finder than I find it faster than I will on my notes
from the previous meeting but some of that had been allocated to asbestos abatement and other things Lancaster rec and SDOL are confirming how much has been spent otherwise but We're expecting that there'll be somewhere between three hundred thousand and five hundred thousand remaining The repairs that we're talking about the HVAC system would be about three hundred to three hundred and seven thousand dollars the elevator upgrade would be about a hundred and fifty thousand and if there's funds remaining that would go to the elevated walkway as well as the the rear the Replacement of the roof platform in the that's right the roof Thank you very much. Dr. Campbell
Since the school district dropped out and they were given the ARPA money we didn't spend any of it on
Renovating price school at this point. It's all being spent on the rec center. Is that correct?
There's a portion that was as director Campbell just explained spent on on asbestos abatement already
Correct
so are we looking to get that back anyway or it's just done do you have any additional comments before we answer additional questions i just want to make sure you have your time and i do want to
say you know the rec center is good but we all know we have lack of youth activities for our
children in the city and we want to know that if we're investing this money is the city going to
children really going to get to use it it's more of a county thing we have i think one
representative from council that sits on the board if I'm correct and just want to know that we have more input if we're the ones that were invested in the ARPA
money from the city not from the county is any of the county municipalities going to add money because they use the rec center as well thank you thank you miss Byrd additional comments from the public on the bill thank you counselor
ideas in regards to the funds I'm interested in finding out why we haven't done anything for the SPCA I mean they've been waiting since June and they still haven't fixed their HVAC so I'm just interested just like everybody in the community that have pets that had when I had to get the wildlife to go rescue 15 cats at a raccoon like they have to be shipped somewhere else which is spending more gas money and more employees and when are we gonna fix that
council Diaz I appreciate your comment but the funds were discussing our ARPA
reallocation the SPCA did not apply for ARPA funds we're not awarded any ARPA funds so I understand your question but it's not tangential to this bill I understand that but it is ARPA money and it is funds thank you any additional comments from the public on the bill hearing none mr. Harris mr. man aye mr.
Roy oh aye mr. Cleese all right miss Craig all right miss Diaz mr. Hirsch
all right president Baker aye I'll take us to the next item on our agenda which resolutions we have resolution number 68 2025 this evening mr. Harris a resolution of the Council of the City of Lancaster authorizing the administration to execute a financial assistance application on behalf of the city to the Pennsylvania infrastructure investment authority and vest for advanced wastewater treatment plant projects South train screening improvements and chlorination facilities improvements motion to approve second we have a motion and a second this is coming up through Public Works I'm not sure if councillor Hershey you have anything or a director Campbell if you have anything additional to share with this one this evening I'm gonna lean on director Campbell for this one I know this is an application for funding but good evening and thank you director Campbell sure thank you very much for this
opportunity as you say this is primarily an administrative request to be able to apply to pen vest for the money that's necessary for the particular projects but I wanted to give a little bit of background and substance behind this there these are the there are two projects the South train screenings improvement and the chlorination facilities improvements the total
project cost is approximately seven point three two million dollars the the city of Lancaster with its partners shares that cost so the part of the cost which which is ascribed to the city of Lancaster is approximately 53 percent of that total seven point three two million and that comes to three point eight seven seven million dollars so that is the amount that we're that we're applying to penvest for the other municipalities will be responsible for making their own applications whether through penvest or through other means
to be able to fill in the difference the purpose is for these two projects one the South train screening improvement which is approximately 3.36 million is
to replace an existing mechanical screen and screening handling equipment with two new mechanical screens and provide increased capacity for full redundancy
for mechanical screening as well as improved screening capture and more
efficient operation and maintenance which will reduce the operations costs of that part of the
facility the second part is the chlorination facilities improvements at the amount of three
point eight six million which is installing an emergency chlorine gas scrubber including an
emergency generator for the chlorination building and control upgrades this critical project would
provide protection for the wastewater treatment plant and the surrounding community in the event
of chlorine gas leak so the overall as I say the overall cost is seven point three two million
dollars fifty three percent of that is ours and we are requesting to make the application for this
and it's fully consistent with a capital plan that was already approved earlier this year in
a virtually those exact same numbers thank you very much dr. Campbell just and to clarify for councils and members of the public this project only these particular projects and functions are for wastewater specifically that's correct thank you
water treatment plant and it's and the variety of supported services that make
sure that we're providing cleaner water back into the conestoga yeah let me take out what we put back thank you very much anything additional council Hirsch yeah I just wanted to clarify so it's called financial assistance and is this a is this a grant from? Penvest or is it a low-interest loan? It's a very good. I'm very glad you asked it. It's a low-interest loan Do we know approximately what kind of interest rate we could expect ballpark? I do not know but
Penvest historically has been the lowest Interest rates that we can get in the market and the reason we do Penvest be a few years ago
We it's we started doing penvest And it was an extraordinary paperwork process to get there But we now know how to do that and do it relatively smoothly because it is the most cost-effective
Low interest loan that we can get Thanks for that context. Thank you additional comments from council on the resolution
comments from the public on the resolution
Hearing none. Mr. Harris Mr.. Men aye mr. Roya aye mr. Cleese aye miss Craig aye Miss Diaz Mr.. Hirsch aye I'm president Baker aye Thank You director Campbell
That concludes our legislative agenda for this evening and will bring us to our second public comment period that's open for Comments on issues not previously discussed on the agenda again duration of comments is three minutes Please begin with your name and block of residence anyone wishing to make public comment please come to the microphone at this time good evening good evening taylor raymond 500 block of saint joseph street and since a couple of people have spoken about the spca i just wanted to give some updates on their instagram five days ago they posted that the essential hvac replacement has finally been scheduled and they're closed starting yesterday through December 11th for that. I don't like that it took this long because it was happening since June like they've had that issue back then but it is finally scheduled.
That's all I've got.
DIRECTOR RIVERA- Thank you.
Additional comments for this period. Good evening again. DIRECTOR DEWOLF- Ijai Gonzalez Toronto block South Ann noticing a gap of communication community and engagement in our quadrant the southeast 50 percent
of registered voters in our areas aren't getting out to the polls at all there's two ordinances that have been enforced that historically have not the alleyway parking and now trash in front of our houses i'm offered an opportunity to be a liaison for our seventh ward precinct five over the last month i've been fostering relationships with 10 families on the 300 and 200 block of south end i've been in communication with corner stores and bodegas from Rockland and Susquehanna to East End and Marshall Street. And I've been mentorship have received mentorship from South Ancona Neighbors where I've been able to run a community meeting and been informed about Lancaster's Leadership Academy. And again I'm here to inform City Council at large if there's issues or topics that are relevant to the community I'm here to pass on the word.
Thank you.
is he's one of the concerned neighbors newer members Darlene Byrd I have three quick issues
I want to speak about one is what Carlos was talking about I mean we talk about these data centers being placed in the city we're talking about our neighborhood where a business is placed in an alleyway things that happened for years Carlos been living there 37 years I lived on
the street 47 years and you could park behind there but now because a business came in nobody
notified us that this business was coming it's there it's big trucks the alleyway is used by our elementary students and our middle school students walking back safety is a major concern we're asking if there's a way that we
can find out what is going to be allowed to be there what's happening next and we
have this neighborhood engagement but it seems like South End is always left out
whether it's a Lancaster City Alliance they don't tell us what streets are being closed in the southeast if it's happening across town you see it posted this street is going to be closed this day from this time and we're getting tired and somebody talked about trust
with our city council members we need that trust we need to know that we can come here and bring issues to you and you're going to hear us the other issue i want to bring up real quick because
i only have three minutes is our interest rates we know that arpa gets interest for money that was there is there anywhere where that's on the budget or where that interest was spent because we know it's a lot and I haven't heard anything or seen anything about it so I would like to ask
that question and um and like he said about the trash and I'm going to meet with Steve about that
afterwards him and I have a meeting set up thank you thank you good evening uh good evening honorable managers of council thank you my name is Bill Simonson I live on the 800 block of role with Javanu like many citizens here tonight and many more who could not make it I come here dismayed to hear that we are getting AI data centers built in our community and the process in which they were approved to be here I think it is the history of America is such that the rich win and often the poor are powerless and Lancaster City to me I'm losing hope in it it seems to be a city that favors the developers the bankers now the tech companies and their wealthy lawyers
well i would ask tonight that city council unfortunately the mayor is not here but that we become a city that favors the little person that favors the mom waiting in line at the water street mission food pantry wondering whether her food stamps are going to come back on then rather that we favor the developers who are going to come in here and pollute our waterways, pollute our airways. They aren't bringing any jobs.
I'm very dismayed. I hope that this council will do everything in its power to stop these data centers from coming to Lancaster and ruining our communities.
Please do what is in your power to put those of us with the least among us first, not the developers. Thank you.
thank you good evening hello hello hello can you hear me okay i am robert potter of i'm gonna say
the 100 block because i don't really know how we do this but i'm over on king street south franklin
anyways three topics for three minutes okay stick with me so it seems like we're going to get these
ai dentist centers no matter how much we oppose them or dislike them my first thing i'm hitting
on is ICE and the police so there's been a glaring lack of the conversation behind ICE this evening and I feel like that is something that is painfully relevant in today's world right now
I believe adding not only the AI data center complementary with red light traffic cameras that we were just talking about beforehand and and it's not just me but I'm gonna hit uh parking enforcement real quick combining all that with strict parking enforcement I don't know if it's just me, but I'm more than sure everyone in here has a ticket they got to pay for or they just paid for. But anyways, it's overbearing. And I do believe with the amount that is being put in into AI and to data centers and to the crappy infrastructure of Lancaster as a whole, I've been here 25 years, it has not really improved that much in the ways that it should. But anyways, I really do think that we are setting ourselves to be crushed under the fascist boot of America.
This is about the most democratic America has felt in like – and I'm talking this room. This is the most democratic it has felt in maybe months. This is the most serious I can take any government right now because we're all sitting here acting like whatever. The person in the White House is in a complete joke that doesn't want us all to suffer in one way or another.
I really think we need to take a step back on these AI data centers.
any and all enforcement that seems to go past the people of the city that don't want anything to do
with this at all at the last meeting we talked about this we said it doesn't benefit the environment doesn't benefit the people doesn't benefit the businesses who is it benefiting the millionaires
billionaires and trillionaires that don't live here don't got to walk on these streets don't eat from these bodegas nothing and it's out of it's out of our question it's almost as if a rapist is in the white house forcing us to do something we don't want to do it is ridiculous
How long are we going to sit here and act like this isn't what democracy is made of? Everyone in this room is ticked at the addition of a data center that's going to benefit nobody. Why is it still happening? Can anybody answer that? Other than money? Exactly.
We've got people on the other side of the globe burning and dying for the exact stuff they are putting in our community.
You think that is any different?
Those data centers are going to clock that you ran that red light, come to your house in the middle of the night, and pick you up. And if you think I am exaggerating, look over in Chicago. Look over at any black and brown community that has anyone living in it across America. It is, I'm not swearing, but it is ridiculous. It is ridiculous. We are sitting here acting like there's a democracy anymore worth protecting, when it is not. It is a joke. It is a joke to get up every morning, work with people's kids, and tell them there's a future worth living and fighting for when the fact of the matter is it's always worth fighting for and living for. But right now, it's for the millionaires and billionaires, not the people in this room that are – and it's all my elders. There's no real younger people here, and I wonder why. It's almost like that notification for this meeting was sent out last minute very quietly. Mr. Palmer, thank you very much. Any additional comments for this period? Okay guys, Susie, 800 block of East Orange Street. I was here in the beginning of the summer and I read this to council. The mayor wasn't here. She's still not here. But let's just hear what I had to say about six months ago. So pushing an ungodly agenda while swearing an oath to protect the people is being rebuked today again. You look down on us by your ignorance and can't believe that the S&P 500 is based on the standard and poor. You see things through the eyes of the wicked who pursue their agenda to, we know, kill, steal, and destroy. There is no unity in this administration because us taxpayers who have expressed ourselves on this podium gets ignored, delayed, or denied. Let's talk, you say. Set up an appointment, but public comments and suggestions, concerns, et cetera, are, you know, we work hard too. Some of us have two or three jobs. We don't have time to talk to you. We pay you to do your job. So Lancaster City has lost its customs, heritage, foundation, its name, Lancaster.
Now it's Lancaster.
And so Lancaster has become the home of survival. To divide and conquer has always been the quest. And you prey on the innocent hard workers because you are too busy closing down departments, relying on IT social technology
with troubleshooting interruptions.
The government creates funding for all cities and states, the workers write the grants, push the intake coordinators to execute the applications to fulfill the needs of the people while they pay their taxes to be the Commonwealth that we both invest in. This is not a one-way street. Your ignorance has taught a generation to measure their work on takeaways as city contracts are being run by outsiders, permitters are forced to use benchmark, Investors are catching tax breaks and shareholders seem to be the only ones receiving equitable gain. For centuries this city relied on volunteers, interns, graduates, and neighborhoods to find an even balance and take care of our public officers while taking pride in the building of infrastructures, cleaning of parks, working together as one so that the baton can be passed to the next graduate who takes pride in the city engagements but this administration has us continuously asking for loans passing on properties to the highest bidder while handing investors a lead abatement condemned properties that can be remedied by community programs such as critical repair government funded funded grants to help in crisis for homelessness lack of housing revitalization so much more instead it's better to pour 80 of a new turf at a baseball field and use that money for that but i think you get the drift and i think you guys get where i'm going so you will go down as the worst administration in lancaster who killed the american dream and broke all the rules i'm sorry but my grandkids they have to live this and for me seeing a future in lancaster city being here 30 plus years i don't see hope and it's shameful 92 properties given to an llc in our city community from sacca when they could have gave it back to the community thank you that doesn't even work here or pay taxes you know there's no return investment which thank you miss gomez are there any additional comments for this period
Tony Dastra, 700 block of New Holland Avenue. Ms. Gomez said I could close it out. So, you know, I just got to say, the young brother speaks the truth, and I appreciate that he's putting his heart and soul out here because it is hard to do. Like, so thank you, because it is important that we remember that ICE is in our community and that we need to do everything to protect the 14th Amendment.
So many issues have been touched on tonight.
this is also complex parking ice data center but i want to use my couple minutes to ask a couple questions and have one comment uh the comment is as we go as we y'all us as the public go through the proposed budget i have always had a little bit of a pit in my stomach when i see tourism under department of neighborhood engagement i don't totally understand why tourism is under department of neighborhood engagement feels like more of a economic development thing so i think
that it deserves to be moved from that department so more resources can go into neighborhood engagement um i understand there might be some things to split up within that group but that's my comment for that uh the two questions i have the first one related to my comments earlier um i don't know how it impacts stuff but the other night at langsey stands up data center meeting it was like hey is there going to be a city council meeting the city council meeting tonight was not on the city's calendar um i don't believe it still is i checked a little bit ago and i do not know how that impacts stuff because the thing i know from sunshine law is agendas and the agenda was posted so just mentioning that as we continue to improve our functions um and then i guess the
other question would be is what what is our plan for improving the communications technology in
this room because it's been we're gonna we'll say eight nine months roughly of this setup uh people are still kind of i saw some people trying to go to the uh lectern that wasn't there tonight because it's not available the public deserves to know when things are going to get back to quote-unquote normal and start to move in a direction of progress that because while this
is look I appreciate the work done to hold measures together we can see how this isn't
working for everybody all the time and we should really get back to normal so that's my second question is what is the plan to get back to normal with our communications thank you thank you any further comments for this period good evening it's just a quick one uh my name is Paul Colbreth uh 34 landis drive lancaster pennsylvania uh i just and i may have talked to a council member or
two about the decommissioned fire station uh i guess number six uh what is the the plan for it uh because i'm i was meeting with a couple organizations that do not have a home there's organizations that are floundering and they had asked me to approach council
about the fire station, number six.
And I wanted to go on record to say
that our organization, NAN,
as well as a couple other organizations are wanting to, would like to take a look at that and would like to throw our hat in the ring before council or the mayor or anybody
dishes that out to a real estate company. So, all right, thank you. Thank you Mr. Kohlbreth. I can follow up when I have specific answers for you. I don't have them this evening. Additional comments for this period? Kevin Batchelor. I live on the 200 block of North Charlotte. Nerve-wracking to talk to all those people but just want to say I moved here a couple years ago and we love it. It's great. It's really cool that we can be in front of this group of
people who I know care. I think this group of people here is probably like me in feeling
pretty disenfranchised and pretty afraid and distrusting of government. And I just filled out a paper today that a lot of your names were on, and I checked the box next to your name, and I feel like I'm doing my job as a citizen. And I just want to know that you
guys are doing your job it uh it's scary you know I see a bunch of people on this panel and
frankly I don't see a ton of care in your faces most of the time I see a lot from the right you guys really seem to care and that's awesome thank you for that I know that this might not be new for you maybe you're all just used to it maybe you're jaded already we need you to not be jaded we need to be in the fight for this community and i need personally man i'm floundering i have like no trust in our larger government i want to see it from at least the people we like share the
community with i've met you all i've seen you i saw you outside of a um you know you asked me to vote for you one time and i did um but that's the last time i saw you and that's weird man and i
know it's maybe not weird for you but it's weird for me and i think it's probably weird for all
you guys so we went to that data center thing and frankly just felt like a joke none of you were
there by the way but that was weird to me too i i really thought you would be there mr aurelio i was shocked that you weren't um maybe you think there's nothing that can be done but i don't think
that's right and I know that this room full of people would love to see you
guys stand up that's all I have to say are there any additional comments for this period I will close public comment this evening that will take us to the
next item on our agenda which is the report of the mayor was not provided
with any from her this evening so we'll move to the next item which is the report of president of council I want to reiterate from my report this evening
two things uh first that although we expected the community benefit agreement to be delivered in full to council for this meeting i was informed just a few days ago that that would likely not happen those meetings and negotiations have been ongoing and i'll just i'll just say i take the fact that it's taking longer to be a good thing because i believe that means we're asking for
things that they're not completely comfortable with i don't know i haven't seen it yet but that's my take um i will be receiving updates later this week and i again remain committed to sharing updates as things move along i have been as transparent as i can be with what i know through this process and i understand completely the frustrations in this room i also understand the feeling of distrust in our government when we have a federal government that is absolutely in chaos dysfunction and on purpose to make us feel this way and i also want to say that i hope that i hope that we don't ever come across that we're operating in that way it's easy to feel like there's a cabal or a conspiracy but something that i've shared with folks that i've been able to meet one-on-one with is that unfortunately there is one and it's just way bigger than we want to admit and it's way bigger and harder to solve than we ever want to admit but i do still believe in the type of government and good government that happens in rooms like this when folks get together and come and share how they feel to local government and local government is at its best when it is not political it should not be political
when we want to pave a street to not be political when we want to get money to improve our infrastructure and I hope that we can continue to do that and provide the stability where we are able and there's a lot of things in this
world that are unstable and desperately outside of our control but again I want to reiterate and thank everyone who've come here to participate and government at this particular level and I would wish that our state and federal representatives would be as accessible and get to hear from you all as well for what it's worth that's my report this evening the next item on our agenda is council comments counselors are there any do you have any comments this evening hearing none and having reached the conclusion of our agenda I'll hear a motion to adjourn motion to adjourn second all in favor aye we are adjourned
thank you